<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?><!DOCTYPE Publisher PUBLIC "-//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN" "http://devel.springer.de/A++/V2.4/DTD/A++V2.4.dtd"><Publisher><!DOCTYPE Publisher PUBLIC "-//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN" "http://devel.springer.de/A++/V2.4/DTD/A++V2.4.dtd"><Publisher>About the AuthorDudley Storey has worked in digital design from the moment his parents bought him his first computer, a Commodore 64 with 16 colors and 64K of memory. Born in New Zealand, he graduated from the University of Auckland with degrees in Art History and Psychology. While continuing to work on more powerful computers, he created digital visualizations, programmable simulations, learning tools, and animations for the manufacturing industry, advertising, and architects. At the age of 28 he moved to Canada and began to teach multimedia at a series of institutions, gaining an increasing specialization in web technologies. While continuing to freelance, he has spent the last decade as an instructor in the New Media Production and Design course at SAIT Polytechnic in southern Alberta.Four years ago, Dudley started a web development blog, <ExternalRef><RefSource>www.demosthenes.info</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="www.demosthenes.info"/></ExternalRef>. Originally intended as a learning aid for his students, the site quickly gained wider attention. Encouraged by questions in his classes, the blog became a center for CSS experimentation and discussion.An enthustiastic contributor to the web development community, Dudley has written for Smashing Magazine, A Student&#x2019;s Guide to Web Design, and other sites.Dudley maintains an active Twitter presence (@dudleystorey) and participates in web design and development conferences around the world, including participation in the W3C Web Education Community Group.When not lecturing, coding, or writing, Dudley enjoys cycling (especially long-distance self-supported bike tours), reading, and film.</Publisher><!DOCTYPE Publisher PUBLIC "-//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN" "http://devel.springer.de/A++/V2.4/DTD/A++V2.4.dtd"><Publisher></Publisher><!DOCTYPE Publisher PUBLIC "-//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN" "http://devel.springer.de/A++/V2.4/DTD/A++V2.4.dtd"><Publisher></Publisher><!DOCTYPE Publisher PUBLIC "-//Springer-Verlag//DTD A++ V2.4//EN" "http://devel.springer.de/A++/V2.4/DTD/A++V2.4.dtd"><Publisher>IntroductionWelcome to Pro CSS3 Animation. This book teaches you how to use the full power of CSS to bring your web content to life with interactivity and a fresh visual approach. In the chapters that follow, you&#x2019;ll learn how to use cutting-edge industry standards to increase the visual appeal, accessibility, and popularity of your site.Who This Book Is ForThis book is designed for designers and coders with at least a few years of experience in web development who wish to rapidly upgrade their skills to the new W3C standards, or who desire to take their explorations of CSS Transforms, Transitions, and Animations in bold new directions. It is not an introductory web design text: the book assumes at least a basic understanding of HTML, CSS, and JavaScript. As web development is a multidisciplinary process, I&#x2019;ll also be addressing issues such as accessibility and semantics, concepts that the reader should be familiar with.How This Book Is StructuredI&#x2019;ve split the book into ten chapters. The first chapters introduce the fundamental components of CSS animation, while later chapters integrate animation with other web technologies.Chapter 1 introduces CSS3, detailing its syntax and development and contrasting it with previous technologies.Chapter 2 covers CSS3 Transforms and Transitions.Chapter 3 shows how to use CSS3 Transitions with images, including gallery effects.Chapter 4 integrates transitions with site user interaction elements such as buttons and menus.Chapter 5 introduces the CSS Animation module.Chapter 6 uses CSS3 Animations on all kinds of web content.Chapter 7 shows how to integrate CSS3 Transitions and Animations with Scalable Vector Graphics (SVG) and CSS Filters.Chapter 8 brings responsive web design and JavaScript together with CSS Animations.Chapter 9 takes Transforms, Transitions, and Animations into the third dimension.Chapter 10 looks to the future of web standards for visual effects and the various tools that can be used to streamline CSS web animation today.Downloading the CodeThe code for the examples shown in this book is available on the Apress web site, <ExternalRef><RefSource>www.apress.com</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="www.apress.com"/></ExternalRef>. A link can be found on the book&#x2019;s information page under the Source Code/Downloads tab. This tab is located underneath the Related Titles section of the page.Contacting the AuthorShould you have any questions or comments&#x2014;or even spot a mistake you think I should know about&#x2014;please feel free to contact me via e-mail (<ExternalRef><RefSource>dudley.storey@gmail.com</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="dudley.storey@gmail.com"/></ExternalRef>) or Twitter (@dudleystorey). I welcome your thoughts and feedback.</Publisher>Contents<ItemContent><Para>About the Authorxiii</Para></ItemContent><ItemContent><Para>Introductionxv</Para></ItemContent>Chapter 1: CSS3 Fundamentals	1Development of CSS	1CSS Vendor Pre&#xFB01;xes	2Vendor Pre&#xFB01;xing Issues	4CSS3 Browser Support	4Limitations of CSS3 Animation	5Design Principles: Progressive Enhancement and Graceful Degradation	6Why CSS3 Rather Than JavaScript or Flash?	6Other Technologies	7Summary	8Chapter 2: CSS3 Transforms and Transitions	9CSS Transforms	9Rotate	10The Webkit CSS3 Transform Aliasing Issue	13Scale	14Translate	16Skew	16Combining Transformations	17CSS Transitions	18Delaying and Combining Transition Effects	21Introducing Easing Functions	22Transition Timing Functions and Bezier Curves	23Summary	29Chapter 3: CSS3 Transitions for Images	31Simple Image CrossFade Effect	31Option 1: First Image As a CSS Background	32Option 2: Both Images As HTML Elements	32Option 3: Both Images As Backgrounds	33A Simple Image Gallery Enhanced with CSS3	34The HTML Markup	34The Initial CSS	35Improving the Gallery	35Adding Captions	36Changing the Initiating Event	36Simple Popup Image Captions	37Image Card Stack and Fan Reveal	40Clapperboard Image Captions with Different Entry and Exit Effects	46Creating Separate Transition Sequences	50Changing the Exit Event	51Background Image Transitions and Animation on Page Load	52Animating the Background Images on Load	54Creating and Animating Fake Background Images	55Summary	56Chapter 4: CSS3 Transitions for UI Elements	57Modern Site Navigation Markup	57Horizontal Navigation Bar Basics	58A Simple Navigation Bar Enhanced with CSS3	59Highlighting the Current Page in Navigation	60Horizontal Tab Navigation with CSS3 Transitions	62Animating Custom Validation Errors for HTML5 Forms	63UI Button Depress Transition	66UI Button Reveal Transition	67Accessible Horizontal Drop-down Navigation with CSS3 Transitions	69Initiating CSS3 Transition Effects After a Button Click	70Animating Form Elements with CSS3	73Summary	74Chapter 5: CSS3 Keyframe Animations	75Keyframes and Tweening	75CSS3 Keyframe Animation Syntax	76Support for Keyframe Animation in Older Browsers	77Controlling Keyframe Animation Playback	78Blending and Chaining Keyframe Animations	79Repeating Animation Sequences	80Pausing Keyframe Animations	83Summary	83Chapter 6: CSS3 Keyframe Animations for Web Content	85A Simple CSS3 Slideshow	85The HTML Code	85A Variation with Background Images	87Pausing the Slideshow	88Altering the Transition Between Images	88Fade-In-Out	88Fade-In-Out During Motion	89CrossFade	90Adding Captions	91An On-Click Method for Pause	92Creating a Fallback for Older Versions of Internet Explorer	93A Caution Against Using Marquee Animation for Text	93News Ticker/Notification Animation	93A Lightbox Image Gallery Equivalent in CSS3	97Adding Captions	99Logo Animation on Page Load	101Summary	102Chapter 7: Integrating CSS3 Animations with SVG and Filters	103An Introduction to SVG	103Placing SVG on a Web Page	104SVG As an Inline Image	104Inline SVG	105SVG Added As an Object or iframe	106Manipulating SVG with CSS	106An Animated SVG Imagemap	108SVG Snowflake Animation	110Tools for SVG	112Introduction to CSS3 Filters	113Summary	115Chapter 8: Integrating CSS3 Animation with Responsive Web Design and JavaScript	117Resizing Elements in Responsive Web Design Without Transitions	118Dynamically Resizing Images and Videos	118Responsive Background Images	120Resizing Elements in Responsive Web Design with Transitions	121Indicating Viewport Size with CSS3 Media Queries and Transitions	123Optimizing CSS Transitions and Animations for Mobile Devices	124Integrating CSS3 Media Queries with SVG	125Triggering CSS3 Transitions with JavaScript	127Customizing CSS3 Transitions with JavaScript	131Summary	133Chapter 9: CSS3 3D Transforms, Transitions, and Animations 	135Perspective	135Rotation	139Translate	140Card Caption Flip	142Backface Visibility	144Transform Style	144A Circular 3D Gallery	145Enhancing the Gallery with Level-4 Selectors and JavaScript	149Adding a CSS Level-4 Selector	1503D CSS Transforms and Transitions for UI Elements	151Summary	154Chapter 10: Tools, Technologies, and the Future of CSS Animation 	155Writing Effective CSS3 Animations and Transitions: Avoiding Reflows	155Automatic Prefixing Tools: Client-Side	157-prefix-free 	157SASS, LESS, Compass and Codekit	158Automatic Prefixing Tools: Server-Side	159GUI-Based CSS3 Animation Tools	159Sencha Animator	159Adobe Edge Animate	160Animatable	160Tumult Hype	161Future Trends: CSS Custom Filters	162Future Trends: Blending and Compositing	164Future Trends: Reconciling CSS3 and SVG	164Summary	164Index	167<Story>Pro CSS3 AnimationCopyright &#x00A9; 2012 by Dudley StoreyThis work is subject to copyright. All rights are reserved by the Publisher, whether the whole or part of the material is concerned, specifically the rights of translation, reprinting, reuse of illustrations, recitation, broadcasting, reproduction on microfilms or in any other physical way, and transmission or information storage and retrieval, electronic adaptation, computer software, or by similar or dissimilar methodology now known or hereafter developed. Exempted from this legal reservation are brief excerpts in connection with reviews or scholarly analysis or material supplied specifically for the purpose of being entered and executed on a computer system, for exclusive use by the purchaser of the work. Duplication of this publication or parts thereof is permitted only under the provisions of the Copyright Law of the Publisher&#x2019;s location, in its current version, and permission for use must always be obtained from Springer. Permissions for use may be obtained through RightsLink at the Copyright Clearance Center. Violations are liable to prosecution under the respective Copyright Law.ISBN-13 (pbk): 978-1-4302-4722-7ISBN-13 (electronic): 978-1-4302-4723-4Trademarked names, logos, and images may appear in this book. Rather than use a trademark symbol with every occurrence of a trademarked name, logo, or image we use the names, logos, and images only in an editorial fashion and to the benefit of the trademark owner, with no intention of infringement of the trademark.The use in this publication of trade names, trademarks, service marks, and similar terms, even if they are not identified as such, is not to be taken as an expression of opinion as to whether or not they are subject to proprietary rights.While the advice and information in this book are believed to be true and accurate at the date of publication, neither the authors nor the editors nor the publisher can accept any legal responsibility for any errors or omissions that may be made. The publisher makes no warranty, express or implied, with respect to the material contained herein.President and Publisher: Paul ManningLead Editor: Louise CorriganTechnical Reviewer: Sylvain GalineauEditorial Board: Steve Anglin, Ewan Buckingham, Gary Cornell, Louise Corrigan, Morgan Ertel, Jonathan Gennick, Jonathan Hassell, Robert Hutchinson, Michelle Lowman, James Markham, Matthew Moodie, Jeff Olson, Jeffrey Pepper, Douglas Pundick, Ben Renow-Clarke, Dominic Shakeshaft, Gwenan Spearing, Matt Wade, Tom WelshCoordinating Editor: Kevin SheaCopy Editor: Elizabeth BerryCompositor: SPi GlobalIndexer: SPi GlobalArtist: SPi GlobalCover Designer: Anna IshchenkoDistributed to the book trade worldwide by Springer Science+Business Media New York, 233 Spring Street, 6th Floor, New York, NY 10013. Phone 1-800-SPRINGER, fax (201) 348-4505, e-mail <ExternalRef><RefSource>orders-ny@springer-sbm.com</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="orders-ny@springer-sbm.com"/></ExternalRef>, or visit <ExternalRef><RefSource>www.springeronline.com</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="www.springeronline.com"/></ExternalRef>. For information on translations, please e-mail <ExternalRef><RefSource>rights@apress.com</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="rights@apress.com"/></ExternalRef>, or visit <ExternalRef><RefSource>www.apress.com</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="www.apress.com"/></ExternalRef>. Apress and friends of ED books may be purchased in bulk for academic, corporate, or promotional use. eBook versions and licenses are also available for most titles. For more information, reference our Special Bulk Sales&#x2013;eBook Licensing web page at <ExternalRef><RefSource>www.apress.com/bulk-sales</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="www.apress.com/bulk-sales"/></ExternalRef>.Any source code or other supplementary materials referenced by the author in this text is available to readers at <ExternalRef><RefSource>www.apress.com</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="www.apress.com"/></ExternalRef>. For detailed information about how to locate your book&#x2019;s source code, go to <ExternalRef><RefSource>www.apress.com/source-code</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="www.apress.com/source-code"/></ExternalRef>.To my grandparents, who never had the chance to read their grandson&#x2019;s first book. &#x2014;Dudley Storey </Story><Story>Photograph by Damain Blunt (<ExternalRef><RefSource>www.damianblunt.ca</RefSource><RefTarget TargetType="URL" Address="www.damianblunt.ca"/></ExternalRef>)</Story></Publisher>